A Guide to the Papers of Mitchell Van Yahres, 1993-2006
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Legislation: Migrant workers: Annual reports of the Virginia Department of Labor and Industry and minutes of the migrant and seasonal farm workers board, 1997-2003 (Folder 9:15)
- Legislation: Open Source Software HB 842, 2003-2004 (Folder 10:1)
- Legislation: Patents (correspondence and research), 2003-2004 (Folder 10:2)
- Legislation: PhotoRed (research), 1999-2001 (Folder 10:3)
- Legislation: PhotoRed (HB 1916, 974, 1860, 2197, 2270, SB 414), 2000-2005 (Folder 10:4)
- Legislation: Pill Bill (HB 154), 2004 (Folder 10:5)
- Legislation: Recordation tax Exemption of business liability (HB 1845), 2004-2005 (Folder 10:6)
- Legislation: Christine Solem SB 1164, 1997-2003 (Folder 10:7)
- Legislation: University of Virginia Pep Band Commendation (HJ 284), 2004 (Folder 10:8)
- Legislation: Water Supply Emergency Ordinance (HB 1631), 2003-2005 (Folder 10:9)
- Legislation: Welfare Diet (HJR 260, HJR 112), 2004 (Folder 10:10)
- Legislation: Wine (interstate license to sell), 1999-2001 (Folder 10:11)
- Personal: miscellaneous, 2003-2004 (Folder 10:12)
- Photograph Album compliments of the House of Delegates, 1999 Session (Folder 10:13)
- Photograph (autographed) President William Jefferson Clinton, n.d. (Folder 10:14)
- Photographs: Mitchell Van Yahres, n.d. (Folder 10:15)
- Photographs: Mitchell Van Yahres, n.d. (Folder 10:16)
- Photographs: Van Yahres, 2001 (Folder 11:1)
- Photographs: negatives (political events), n.d.; 2001; 2003 (Folder 11:2)
- Photographs: Piedmont Community College, n.d. (Folder 11:3)
- Photograph: Governor Charles Robb and Van Yahres, n.d. (Folder 11:4)
- Photograph: Governor Mark Warner and Van Yahres, n.d. (Folder 11:15)
- Publications honoring Van Yahres (CHIP), 2005 (Folder 11:6)
- Race relations: Charlottesville history, 2003 April 12 (Folder 11:7)
- Resumes: Van Yahres, n.d. (Folder 11:8)
- Retirement: Van Yahres, 2005 (Folder 11:9)
- Role of State Government, n.d. (Folder 11:10)
- Speeches and notes, 1971-2000 (Folder 11:11)
- Speeches and notes, n.d. (Folder 11:12)
- Speeches File, 2001-2003 (Folder 11:13)
- Speeches File, 2004-2005 (Folder 11:14)
- Taxes: Budget, 2002 (Folder 11:15)
- Taxes: local and state, 2001-2004 (Folder 11:16)
- Taxes 2004, 2004 (Folder 11:17)
- Transportation, 1999-2004 (Folder 11:18)
- Transportation: Meadowcreek Parkway, 2000-2002 (Folder 11:19)
  Correspondents on these issues include former mayor Maurice Cox, former mayor Blake Caravati, Stephen D. Newman, L. Preston Bryant, and Robert Hodous.
- Transportation: Roundabout HJ 594, 1999-2003 (Folder 12:1)
- Transportation: Roundabout Chville-Albemarle Airport, 2002-2004 (Folder 12:2)
- Transportation: Route 29 Bypass, 1996-2002 (Folder 12:3)
- Transportation: Route 29 Bypass SB 670, 2004 (Folder 12:4)
- Transportation: Transdominion Express, Transportation: Transdominion Express (Folder 12:5)
- T.V. Community Access, 1993-2005 (Folder 12:6)
- University of Virginia: Charles Bly, 2002 (Folder 12:7)
  Bly was a University of Virginia nuclear physicist who charged that the administration and faculty abused his nuclear engineering PhD program. The folder contains his letter to the University, the Federal government and state politicians.
- University of Virginia: Budget; State, 2004 January 1 (Folder 12:8)
- University of Virginia: Charter, 2004-2005 (Folder 12:9)
  Correspondents include University of Virginia faculty member Jeffrey Rossman, University of Virginia spokesperson Nancy Rivers, Legislators Creigh Deeds, Steven Landes and many others.
- University of Virginia: City of Charlottesville, 2002-2003 (Folder 12:10)
  There is material showing the attempts of Mitchell Van Yahres to improve communication between the University of Virginia and the City of Charlottesville. Van Yahres met several times with University of Virginia Board member William Crutchfield to discuss ways that the University could share information with the city about its meetings, plans and activities.
- University of Virginia: Heating Plant, 2002 (Folder 12:11)
- University of Virginia: Hospital Complaints, 2002 (Folder 12:12)
- University of Virginia: Living Wage, 2002 (Folder 12:13)
- University of Virginia: Dr. James S. McCarthy, 2001-2002 (Folder 12:14)
  Includes a report by the American Association of University Professors (AAUP) concerning the dismissal of Dr. James S. McCarthy based on a charge that he misused grant monies. The report includes a rebuttal letter from University of Virginia President John Casteen. The folder also contains correspondence between McCarthy and Mitchell Van Yahres. McCarthy was a tenured professor of physics and Director of the university's Institute of Nuclear and Particle Physics.
- University of Virginia: NAACP, 2002 (Folder 12:15)
  There is information in the topical files on the University of Virginia and the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP), specifically a letter from Priscilla L. Whiting, Chair of Education at the Albemarle Charlottesville branch of the NAACP to the University of Virginia President John Casteen where she strongly suggests that there is racial disparity at the University.
- University of Virginia: Parking Garage: news clippings and complaints, 2002 (Folder 13:1)
- University of Virginia Parking Garage: Van Yahres notebook, 2002 May-July (Folder 13:2)
- University of Virginia: Parking Garage, 2002 January-June (Folder 13:3)
  There is extensive information on the University of Virginia's construction of the parking garage on Emmet Street and the University's interactions with the City of Charlottesville. Relating to the construction of the parking garage, there is significant correspondence between the University of Virginia, the City of Charlottesville, some of the state agencies of Virginia and the constituents of Charlottesville. Specifically the correspondents are University of Virginia President John Casteen, University of Virginia executive vice president and chief operating executive Leonard Sandridge, University of Virginia Rector John P. Ackerly III, University of Virginia Board member William Crutchfield, University of Virginia spokesperson Nancy Rivers, Director of University of Virginia facilities Robert P. Dillman, Virginia Secretary of Administration Sandra D. Bowen, Virginia Department of Environmental Quality Ellie Irons, Virginia Director of Economic Development Aubrey Watts, former mayor Maurice Cox, former mayor Blake Caravati, former mayor Meredith Richards, Congressman Creigh Deeds, President of the Lewis Mountain Neighborhood Arthur Lichtenberger, Wilbur Smith Associates, Glatting Jackson Kercher Anglin Lopez Rinehart Consulting Firm, Parson Brinkerhoff (traffic study), Virginia Department of Transportation representative Angel Deem, Virginia Director of Transportation Planning and Environmental Affairs Jeffrey C. Southard, Virginia Department of Transportation representative Karen Kilby, Director of Virginia Department of Environmental Quality Robert G. Burnley, Congressman John J. Davies III, House Appropriations Committee representative Tony Maggio (provides a timeline of parking garage issues) and the law firm Feil Pettit and William and attorneys David B. Franzen and S. Craig Brown (city attorney). The files include drawings of the parking garage; a chronological account of the developments; arguments for reviewing traffic studies; discussions about payment for delaying construction and the need for cooperation between the University and the city, as well as correspondence from constituents and attorneys.
- University of Virginia: Parking Garage, 2002-2003 (Folder 13:4)
- University of Virginia: Projects, 2002 (Folder 13:5)
  There is information regarding the University of Virginia on other projects. Under the General Obligation Bond there are plans for a heating plant, concert hall and thirteen other projects. Correspondence is included from the University of Virginia Vice President for Management & Budget Colette Sheehy.
- Van Yahres: news clippings, 1999-2000 (Folder 14:1)
- Van Yahres: news clippings, 2001 February- December (Folder 14:2)
- Van Yahres: news clippings, 2002 January- May (Folder 14:3)
- Van Yahres: news clippings, 2002 June-December (Folder 14:4)
- Van Yahres: news clippings, 2003 January- June (Folder 14:5)
- Van Yahres: news clippings, 2003-2004 (Folder 14:6)
- Van Yahres: news clippings, 2004 February- March (Folder 14:7)
- Van Yahres: news clippings (Abortion/birth, campaign, community), 2002-2002 (Folder 14:8)
- Van Yahres: news clippings (topic), 2001-2002 (Folder 14:9)
  There are topics including abortion/births, campaign, community, education, eugenics, judicial, miscellaneous, money, photo/red, spanking by foster parents, and voting rights.
- Van Yahres: news clippings miscellaneous, 1968-1975 (Folder 15:1)
- Van Yahres: news clippings miscellaneous, n.d.; 1981-2005 (Folder 15:2)
- Calendars, 1987-1993 (Folder 16:1)
- Calendars, 1994-1998 (Folder 16:2)
- Datebooks monthly, 1999-2001 (Folder 16:3)
- Datebooks monthly, 2002-2004 (Folder 16:4)
- Datebooks yearly, 2003 (Folder 16:5)
- Datebooks yearly, 2004 (Folder 16:6)
- Pocket datebooks, 1994-1995 (Folder 16:7)
- Pocket datebooks, 1996 (Folder 16:8)
- Pocket datebooks, 1997 (Folder 16:9)
- Pocket datebooks, 1998 (Folder 17:1)
- Pocket datebooks, 1999 (Folder 17:2)
- Pocket datebooks, 2003 (Folder 17:3)
- Letters of congratulations for receiving the McIntire Award, 1975-1976 (Folder 18:1)
- Outstanding Legislator Award/Virginia Young Democrats, 1983 (Folder 18:2)
- 1988-2005 Certificates/awards: Virginia Young Democrats; Equality Virginia; Childcare Provider Recognition Day; Legislator Hero/Virginia League of Conservation Voters; Second Sight Club; Organ tissue and donation (Folder 18:3)
- Outstanding service on the House Joint Resolution no. 24 providing Airport Safety Zoning/Virginia Department of Aviation, 1989 August 24 (Folder 18:4)
- Outstanding service to young children in Virginia/Virginia Association for Early Childhood Education, 2005 (Folder 18:5)
- President's Award in appreciation of outstanding service/Virginia League of Social Services Executives, 2000 April 12 (Folder 18:6)
- Virginia Housing Coalition recognizes the Honorable Mitchell Van Yahres for his leadership in promoting affordable housing, 2000 September 14 (Folder 18:7)
- Community service award/ Beta Kappa Chapter-Sigma Theta Tau International, 2002 (Folder 18:8)
- A.L. Philpott Award for Outstanding Service/Democratic Party of Virginia, 2002 (Folder 18:9)
- Recognizing his commitment to Serving Children and Family in Virginia/Jefferson Area CHIP, 2005 (Folder 18:10)
- Tribute to Mitchell VanYahres in honor of dedication and service to the Recording for the Blind and Dyslexia, 2005 April 25 (Folder 18:11)
- In Appreciation for 24 years of Dedicated Service to the Albemarle County Police Department, 2005 May 12 (Folder 18:12)
- Thanks/Region Ten Community Service Board, 2005 July 3 (Folder 18:13)
- Audiocassette: 0605 Community Focus: Virginia Festival of the Book, n.d. (Folder 19)
- Videocassette: 0605 Community Focus: Monticello Virtua Village; Sprint Centel Community Service, April 1, 1995 (Folder 19)
- Videocassette: 0605-a Community Focus: Qualchoice for State Employees; Tobacco Communities Project, April 1, 1995 (Folder 19)
- Videocassette: 0605-b Community Focus: Recording for the Blind and Dyslexic, 1995 (Folder 19)
- Videocassette: 0605-c Community Focus: Neighborhood Playgrounds, 1995 (Folder 19)
- Videocassette: 0605-d Community Focus: Housing and Urban Development, 1996 (Folder 19)
- Videocassette: 0605-e Community Focus: Neighborhood Association, 1996 (Folder 19)
- Videocassette: 0605-f Community Focus: Piedmont Council of the Arts, 1997 (Folder 19)
- Videocassette: 0605-g Community Focus: Tourism, 1997 (Folder 19)
- Videocassette: 0605-h Community Focus: Camp Holiday Trails, 1997 (Folder 19)
- Videocassette: 0605-i Community Focus: March of Dimes; Discovery Museum; Tourism, 1997 (Folder 19)
- Videocassette: 0605-j Community Focus: Paul Lombardo, 2001 (Folder 19)
- Videocassette: 0605-k Community Focus: Public Defender, 2001 (Folder 19)
- Videocassette: 0605-l Community Focus: Bob De Mauri;Lindy Cockman, 2001 (Folder 19)
- Videocassette: 0605-m: Community Focus: Region X; Peter Sheras and Jim Peterson, 2003 (Folder 19)
- Videocassette: 0605-n: Virginia: Outreach Virginia; Maureen Wellen; Laura Hawthorn, 2002-2003 (Folder 19)
- Videocassette: 0605-o: Community Focus: Laurie McDade; Roseanne Simeone, 2002 (Folder 19)
- Videocassette: 0605-p: Community Focus: MACAA Monticello Area Community Action Agency, 2003 (Folder 19)
- Videocassette: 0605-q: Community Focus: Creigh Deeds, 2003 (Folder 19)
- Videocassette: 0605-r: Community Focus: CATEC Charlottesville Albemarle Technical Education Center, 2003 (Folder 19)
- Videocassette: 0605-s: Community Focus: Tom Vanderer; Herman Key; Independent Research Center, 2003 (Folder 19)
- Videocassette: 0605-t: Community Focus: Mental Health Association, n.d. (Folder 19)
- Videocassette: 0605-u: Community Focus: Mary Ann Elwood; Malcolm Jarrell; Marcia Invernizzi, n.d. (Folder 19)
- Videocassette: 0605-v: Community Focus: Lee Danielson, n.d. (Folder 19)
- Videocassette: 0605-w: Community Focus: Opportunity Knocks, n.d. (Folder 19)
- Videocassette: 0605-x: Peter Way/Ubben Campaign, 1997 (Folder 19)
- Videocassette: 0605-z: WVPT Consider This, n.d. (Folder 19)
- Videocassette: 0605-aa: VCTA Cable Reports from the Virginia General Assembly; Creigh Deeds, Van Yahres, n.d. (Folder 19)
- Videocassette: 0605-ab: General Assembly Adjournment, n.d. (Folder 19)
- Photographs of Mitch Van Yahres; one photograph of David Toscano, n.d., O.S. (Folder 1)
- Newspaper advertisement campaigns, n.d., O.S. (Folder 2)
- Newspapers: The Daily Progress and The Tribune, n.d., O.S. (Folder 3)
- Official certificates for member of House of Delegates and Governor appointed trustee of Board of Chippokes Plantation Farm 1982-2002, O.S. (Folder 4)
- Poster to Re-Elect Van Yahres; hand-made posters saying thank you to Van Yahres for his visit from Clark School and Mrs. Akers class, n.d., O.S. (Folder 5)
- Map of 57th House District, n.d., O.S. (Folder 6)
- Map of Branchlands Precinct 57th House District, 2001, O.S. (Folder 7)
- Map of Free Bridge Precinct, 2001, O.S. (Folder 8)
- Map of Charlottesville Area, 2001, O.S. (Folder 9)